<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<note type="terminology" subject="MEOW COT">
  <title>MEOW COT Terminology Note</title>
  <summary>This note records a provenance-aware terminology decision for MEOW-style COT.</summary>

  <section id="verdict" title="Verdict">
    <item>In MEOW, COT does not mean a separate per-section reasoning trace.</item>
    <item>In the released paper and repo, COT means a distilled, visible rationale that bridges references to the final outline in two global steps.</item>
    <item>A more precise label for the released artifact is taxonomy-to-outline rationale or distilled outline rationale.</item>
    <item>Clustering or taxonomy alone is only Step 1 of that process, not the full name of the artifact.</item>
  </section>

  <section id="what-the-paper-says" title="What The Paper Says">
    <source-paper>
      <paper-title>Meow: End-to-End Outline Writing for Automatic Academic Survey</paper-title>
      <arxiv-id>2509.19370</arxiv-id>
      <published>2025-09-19</published>
      <url>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19370</url>
    </source-paper>
    <paper-claim scope="terminology">
      <item>Section 3.2 says DeepSeek-R1 is used to derive a taxonomy from references through clustering and then construct the logical deduction chain linking input references to the final outline.</item>
      <item>This makes the paper-level notion of CoT broader than taxonomy alone.</item>
    </paper-claim>
  </section>

  <section id="what-the-released-repo-does" title="What The Released Repo Does">
    <primary-local-sources>
      <source path="/Users/xjp/Desktop/Outline_COT/resources/Meow-Data-curation/utils/add_cot/add_cot.py">add_cot.py</source>
      <source path="/Users/xjp/Desktop/Outline_COT/resources/Meow-Data-curation/utils/add_cot/deepseek.py">deepseek.py</source>
      <source path="/Users/xjp/Desktop/Outline_COT/resources/Meow-Data-curation/utils/data_to_trainformat/formet_to_train_data.py">formet_to_train_data.py</source>
      <source path="/Users/xjp/Desktop/Outline_COT/docs/meow_prompt_pack.json">meow_prompt_pack.json</source>
    </primary-local-sources>
    <observed-behavior>
      <item>
        <statement>The cot prompt in add_cot.py explicitly asks for exactly two steps.</statement>
        <evidence path="/Users/xjp/Desktop/Outline_COT/resources/Meow-Data-curation/utils/add_cot/add_cot.py" line="24"/>
        <steps>
          <step>cluster references into themes aligned with real section or subsection headings</step>
          <step>explain how those themes produce the complete outline</step>
        </steps>
      </item>
      <item>The prompt also includes "Target Outline:{outline}", so the released cot is written with access to the gold outline rather than generated independently first.</item>
      <item>
        <statement>The DeepSeek wrapper returns both visible message.content and hidden message.reasoning_content, but add_cot.py stores only the visible answer into item["cot"].</statement>
        <evidence path="/Users/xjp/Desktop/Outline_COT/resources/Meow-Data-curation/utils/add_cot/add_cot.py" line="66"/>
      </item>
      <item>
        <statement>During SFT packing, formet_to_train_data.py prepends &lt;think&gt;{cot}&lt;/think&gt; before the outline. In the released formatter, this cot is visible supervision text, not DeepSeek's hidden native reasoning trace.</statement>
        <evidence path="/Users/xjp/Desktop/Outline_COT/resources/Meow-Data-curation/utils/data_to_trainformat/formet_to_train_data.py" line="93"/>
      </item>
    </observed-behavior>
  </section>

  <section id="terminology-decision" title="Terminology Decision">
    <usage mode="following-meow-own-usage">
      <item>COT is acceptable, but it should be understood as an explicit outline-construction rationale distilled after seeing the target outline.</item>
    </usage>
    <usage mode="stricter-wording-to-avoid-confusion">
      <item>Do not treat released MEOW COT as native model reasoning.</item>
      <item>Do not treat released MEOW COT as a pure taxonomy artifact.</item>
      <item>Prefer taxonomy-to-outline rationale for the released artifact.</item>
      <item>Prefer section-aligned taxonomy scaffold for a stricter artifact where each section would have its own local taxonomy or reasoning unit.</item>
    </usage>
  </section>

  <section id="practical-reading-rule" title="Practical Reading Rule">
    <item>When reading any refs/&lt;paper_id&gt;/COT.md in this repo, interpret it as a post-hoc, two-step rationale aligned to the stored outline.</item>
    <item>Do not assume it is a section-by-section derivation.</item>
    <item>Do not assume it is the hidden reasoning_content emitted by DeepSeek-R1.</item>
  </section>

  <section id="assumptions" title="Assumptions">
    <item>This note follows the released MEOW paper and released repo behavior, not a broader external standard where CoT must refer only to native hidden reasoning.</item>
    <item>This note does not rename files, alter prompts, or change dataset fields.</item>
  </section>
</note>
